Okay, folks. Uh,
my
floating controls disappeared.
Give me a second, folks. Zoom seems to
have messed up, so I can't see my
controls anymore. I'm going to have to
quit and come back.
Hello. Can everybody hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Good.
Oh, wait. Let's Let's start it. Let's
begin.
Uh we have completed our series of
lectures on
the basic idea of neural networks
multi-layer perceptrons and how we can
train it. So now we are moving on to our
next series of topics namely
convolutional neural networks.
So uh
the story so far MLPS are universal
function approximators.
They can model boolean functions,
classifiers and regressions. And they
can be trained through v variations of
gradient descent for which gradients can
be computed by back propagation.
And the kind of model we've looked at so
far was like this. It was a multi-layer
perceptron where you received some
inputs and pass them pass these inputs
sequentially through many layers of
neurons until you computed your outputs.
And these could recognize patterns in
data. any kind of data like digits or
any other kind of vector data. So now we
have a new kind of problem.
I have say a recording of this kind. I
know the length. It's always 1 second
long and uh I'm asked to determine I'm
asked to determine if the recording
includes the word welcome. When we get a
recording of this kind, the first thing
you do is to convert it to a sequence of
vectors like a spectrogram.
And then if it's just a problem of
classification
and we were to treat this using standard
classification uh uh strategies, we just
construct an MLP which looks at the
entire input and tells you if the
recording contains the word welcome or
not.
But then my question to you guys is
this. Suppose I've trained a neural
network that can recognize the word
welcome when it occurs in the initial
portion of the recording over here. Will
the same network also recognize that the
recording includes the word welcome if
it occurs in the second half of the
recording? Like so? What do you guys
think? Would a network that rec that
detects welcomes and recordings of this
kind also perform well and recordings of
the second kind? What do you guys think?
So see no, right? Why no?
Why not necessarily
the correct answer is no. And it has to
do with the fact that let's say you
thought of this recording as a vector.
If I unravel the vector, the vector is
going to look something like this.
Right?
Then in the first sit first case, the
pattern appears over here.
So you can think of this if I were to
reduce it to a series of zeros and ones
would have zeros here and ones here and
zeros here.
In the second case, this recording is
going to become a vector of this kind
where the pattern occurs here. So if I
were to reduce it to zeros and ones,
you'd have zeros out here including in
the locations where you had once in the
previous one and the ones would be down
here. So these two vectors are entirely
different. If you were to think about it
in three dimensions, this is like the
xaxis. This would be the z-axis or
something of that kind, right? So these
two recordings are completely different
just by changing the position of the par
target pattern.
So what we need is a simple network that
will fire that will say yes if the
recording includes the word welcome
regardless of the location of the word
and if the recording doesn't include
welcome it should say no it should not
fire.
Similarly, consider images. Suppose I
were to train a network to detect
flowers and images.
Then
if I were to train a network that could
recognize flowers if they up appeared in
the top left corner, would the same MLP
also give you the correct answers if the
flower was in the bottom right corner?
Would it do so? Yes or no?
What do you guys think? No. Why not?
Again, why not? Different vector
representations. They're in different
positions, which means this vector is
entirely different from this vector. So
once again, we need a network that will
fire regardless of the precise location
of the target pattern. So these are
examples where the location of the
pattern is not important. The location
of the flower is not important or the
location of the word welcome is not
important. Only the presence of the
pattern is important. And conventional
MLPS are sensitive to the location of
the pattern. So if I move the whole
location by just one component, the uh
as far as the vectors are concerned, the
vectors are entirely different. they
live in different subspaces and the MLP
won't recognize it. What we need is a
network that's shift invariant meaning
if you shift the target pattern around
in the input it should still fire. So uh
can anybody suggest how we could build
such a network which is shift invariant
for say the welcome problem. How would
we do this? anyone
data augmentation. So explain data
augmentation
you would say so you're suggesting that
I can provide training data with
welcomes at every position and then if I
do so then it would actually learn to
find welcome everywhere. The problem is
you're going to need a really large
network for it to be able to recognize
the word welcome in every possible
position and you're going to need an
enormous amount of data in order to with
welcomes occur occurring in every
possible position. So yeah, it's a
reasonable solution but it's not a very
meaningful solution. A better solution
is as uh someone
uh a better solution is as someone
mentioned
to scan
So you can build a an MLP that recognize
let's say you know the approximate
length of the word welcome then you can
build an MLP that looks at an input for
of that size and so you can use it and
now try to detect if the word welcomes
occurs here and then scan the input for
this for the word welcome. come and now
this network the scanning is going to
produce one output at every position.
Right? So if it produc but my question
is does this entire recording contain
the word welcome or not? What I got was
an answer at every position. So how do I
combine all of these to get one answer?
Anyone? How would I combine these? R.
Perfect. Right. So, the correct answer
is R. How do you How would you do an R
in this case?
How would you do an R in this case?
Anyone?
So, here's what happens. If the
recording contains the word welcome,
then at at least one of these positions,
this output is going to be very close to
one. If the recording does not contain
the word welcome at none of the
positions will the output be close to
one. Does that give you a hint how how I
could combine these outputs?
Anyone that give you a hint?
Take the maximum right and so not the
arg.
And if any of these is high then the
overall output is high and the the
overall output is close to one. I know
that the recording includes the word
welcome. That make sense to everybody?
And if there's no welcome in it, the max
will be small. And so you can say the
recording doesn't have the word welcome.
Now
you don't need to have a max. The max
can be computed using a perceptron,
right? We know this. And if you want to
account for small bits of variation and
the scale of things, then you could even
have an MLP out here. But the basic idea
remains the same. You detect a a welcome
detector and then construct a welcome
detector and then scan the input,
produce an output at each position, and
then combine those outputs using a MAX
or a or or a softmax or an entire NLP.
And that's going to tell you if the
recording contained the word welcome. Is
does this make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right. Right. So,
how exactly did we do this? Somebody
asked me, "What do you mean by
scanning?" Here's what you do. You would
go through the input. So, the input is
long. So, you're going to start from the
first position and go left to right.
At each position, you're going to chunk
chunk out a little segment
and then you pass that segment through
an MLP. And so this MLP is going to give
you an output for this position. So you
do this for every position. You're going
to get an output at every position. And
this collection of YTS is then put
through the softmax to give you the
overall output. So is the pseudo code
making sense to all of you guys? what
we're doing here.
Yes. So, okay.
Uh
well, if it contains more than just one
word, just just the word welcome, if if
it's a welcome detector, it's not going
to fire for the other words, other
instances, other words. If you have more
than one instance of welcome, that's
great, too. It means it the recording
includes the word welcome. So Jesse,
because
if the recording contains the word
welcome, then at least one of these is
going to be high. So if I look at the
max, the max tells me that there was at
least one. And if the max is one, it
means that there was a word there was
the word welcome was detected at at
least one position. That answer, Jesse?
Okay.
But then it's actually just one giant
network. How so?
These are all little networks looking at
little windows of the input. Their
outputs are being combined through a
softmax or a perceptron or a multi-layer
perceptron. So does this whole thing not
look like just one big network. If I
were to just draw this, this would be
just one big network. Would it not be?
Yes or no?
So what's the distinction between this
and a regular network that you of the
kind that you've seen before?
What's the difference?
Anyone?
So the difference is that at the lowest
layer you have many copies of the subnet
which is basically this network scanning
the input. And so the network itself has
many subnets.
Each of them looking at a different
portion of the input. And all of these
subnets are identical.
You're training the whole network. That
make sense to everybody
that these right? And of course by doing
this this network has become shift
invariant.
So this whole thing is just like one
large network. This is the final layer
of the overall MLP. I can just write
giant MLP out here. Right? So those
subnets are proportional to the length
of the pattern that you're
trying to detect. If I want to detect if
the record if the image contains a
flower, I could construct an MLP to look
at a region of the input that
corresponds to the size of the flower
that I expect to detect. And then I can
scan the input for the flower and I'm
going to get one output at every
position and the image. And then I could
just take a max over all of these or
maybe put it through a soft max or a
perceptron. And the overall output is
going to tell me if this image included
a flower or not.
That make sense to everybody,
right? We just did.
So again, here is the uh pseudo code.
Now you're going from left to right, but
you're also going from top to bottom
because you're scanning the input like
so. Right?
And then at each position, you're
chunking out a little window, which is
this guy. And you're passing that window
through an NLP that's going to give you
one output for that position. So you'll
get outputs for every position. The
collection of outputs is an output for a
softmax. That gives you gives you the
output of the overall network. So this
pseudo code explaining things to me to
to you guys
like does this make sense to everyone?
Okay,
once again this is just one giant
network, right? This entire operation we
have little subnets looking at different
windows and they all connect to a final
softmax or an MLP. And so this is going
to be just this is just one uh giant
network with one key feature. All the
subnets are identical. And so this
network is shift invariant and that if
you move the basic pattern around it's
uh
still going to give you the same
output concept.
Right? So do you see how this is
shifting
this guy?
Yes or no?
Okay. Do respond guys.
And so in the 2D case too, this whole
thing is just one network where this is
just the final layer of the overall MLP.
I could just write giant NLP and
everything works right. So that's it.
Now, here is your first phone.
All right, guys. 10 seconds.
10 seconds.
Let's stop it right here.
Uh,
what's the answer to the first question?
True or false?
First one, true or false. Second one,
true or false.
Perfect. Right. Both statements are
true.
Now I'm going to just change the picture
a little bit. I was showing MLPS in this
manner, this layered uh network. And so
when I visualizing scanning with an MLP,
the picture I showed was something of
this kind where the same MLP analyzes
the input at each position and uh then
those things their outputs are combined
for the final overall output. Right? But
then this kind of illustration has a
problem. The x-axis in my in my in my
example represents time. So if I drew
this picture like this, it seems to give
the impression that this yellow neuron
is computed after this red neuron. So
they gives seems to give an impression
within each layer. But that's not true.
What happens is that the entire network
is computed at each position. So rather
than an illustration of this kind, this
is a more valid representation. This
first layer is computed on some input.
This this is the second layer. All the
neurons in the second layer are
connected to all the neurons in the
first layer. All the neurons in the
third layer are connected to all the
neurons in the second layer. And this
entire computation is done at one
position. So can you guys see why this
is a more appropriate illustration than
this one?
Can you guys see this?
Yes or no?
Because this seems to indicate that this
is time but it's not time. Right? So I'm
going to use this illustration and I'm
going to simplify things a little bit
further. I won't actually draw all these
arrows. I'm just going to draw a simple
arrow of this kind. What this means is
that these layer 1 neurons connect to
all the inputs between these these two
positions. All the neurons in the second
layer connect to all the neurons in the
first layer. All the neurons in the
third layer connect to all the neurons
in the second layer and so on. This
scanning when visualized in this manner
is actually going to look like this
where I'm scanning I'm looking for a
pattern which is two inputs wide in this
example. And so this entire
network is analog inputs then it's
stepping forward by two time steps and
then analyzing these two inputs then
then all of their outputs are going into
the final uh decision layer of the
network. So, is this illustration making
sense to you guys?
Yes or yes or no?
Okay. And here's what you'd get if you
were stepping forward by one time step
instead of two. This is what an actual
scan would do, right? So
again going back to our uh lecture when
I'm scanning a picture I am scanning the
input with an MLP and basically I'm
computing the same MLP at every position
all of their outputs are going to the
final decision uh layer or network.
Similarly in the 1D case when I'm
scanning some say like a speed signal
I'm scanning the entire input with the
network and all their outputs are going
into the final decision uh machine. So
once but then these things are just
giant networks and once you realize that
you you realize that you can just train
them using back propagation using
conventional back propagation. So if I
want to train a flower detector, I don't
actually have to mark out the position
of the flower. I can provide a
collection of images with and without
flower.
I can have just have a collection of
recordings with and without the word
welcome in it. And that should be enough
to train this network. I don't actually
have to identify where in the input the
word welcome has occurred because this
scanning bit has been figured out
figured into the overall network itself.
Yet in the process you will somehow
magically also learn the lower level
flower or welcome detector. This making
sense to everybody
what we just said.
I see a single yes. What about the rest
of you guys?
Okay.
So one thing when you're training the
network you have to take into account
something else.
You have to train into take into account
that all of these subnets are identical.
Right? So this is what is called a
shared parameter network. If I train
this network and I make an update to
this subnet, the same update must be
made to all of these subnets because
it's the same subnet scanning the entire
input. Similarly, if I make an update to
this guy, that update has to be
reflected in all of these because
they're all identical. That make sense?
Yes or no
to all of you guys? Okay. So, how does
that math work? Right. So these are all
shared parameter networks. These lower
level subnets are identical. So any
update to one copy must equally update
all the copies.
Let's see how that can be done. Uh we
can
the way we do it is I'm going to
generalize this. How many subnets you
don't need you're scanning right? So
it's it's going to depend on the size of
the input bracket. Anyways uh this is uh
let's consider this. These are all
special instances of what are called
shared parameter networks. What is a
shared parameter network? A shared
parameter network is one where you
decide for some reason that some subsets
of parameters must have identical
values. For example, if I decide that
these two edges in this network must
always have the same weight for whatever
reason, what does this mean? that this
edge
equals this edge and both of them equal
some common shared value. So when I make
updates, I won't be making updates to
this guy. I will actually be making
updates to the shared value which will
get copied to both of these guys. Is
this making sense?
The notion of a shared parameter
network,
right? So
how does that work? How does a shared
parameter network work? Here's what
happens. This shared parameter WS
directly influences the shared value
directly influences both these weights
and both these weights influence the
divergence. Right? So when I want to
compute the derivative of the divergence
with respect to WS, I have to take
derivatives down both paths. So the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to WS is going to be the
respect to this weight times the
derivative of this weight with respect
to WS plus the derivative of the
divergence with respect to this weight
times the derivative of this weight with
respect to WS. So that's what this
equation shows right. But then I'm
literally copying this guy over here.
I'm copying this guy over here. So what
is the derivative on this edge? What is
the derivative of W ln with respect to
WS? What is this derivative? Anybody?
One. Similarly, what is this derivative?
That's also one. So, these guys just
become one. And so, the derivative of
the divergence with respect to the
shared value simply becomes the sum of
the derivatives of the divergence with
respect to each of the terms that share
that value. And so for any given
training instance when you pass the
derivatives down you're going to get
some derivative over here and some
derivative over here. They need not be
identical but then you sum them up to
get the derivative with respect to the
common shared WS and then once you do
that you can use that derivative in the
update. So uh overall when you're
performing training so you would have uh
Christian how is it I'm saying WL equals
WS. What is the derivative of WL with
respect to WS? Christian,
if you have this relationship, what is
the derivative of this guy with respect
to this?
What would it be? Christian,
right? It's got to be one, right? If a=
b d / da is always one. So
now if you have a network of this kind
then
in your shared parameter network you
know that these guys have identical
weights right similarly you know that
these guys have identical weights so you
have many sets of edges which have the
same weight so I would be computing the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to this common value for all of
these guts which is simply going to be
the sum sum over all of these edges
which share this common value of the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to these weights and that
is what you' use to update your network
parameters. So for every set S where all
of these red guys are one set, all of
these blue guys are one set and so on,
you want to compute the derivative of
the loss with respect to the shared
value. Then you want to update the
shared value and then copy the shared
value over to each of the W's. And then
what is the derivative of this loss with
respect to the shared value? The
derivative of the loss with respect to
the shared value. For that you go over
all the elements in the set and sum the
derivatives of the divergence with
respect to those elements. So for
example here if these guys have a shared
value then you'll be going over all of
these guys compute the derivative of the
loss with respect to each of these guys
and sum them up. And when you sum them
up you're going to come up end up with
the derivative of the loss with respect
to the shared value. And that derivative
with respect to the shared value is what
you would use in the gradient descent.
And then having updated WS, you would
copy WS back into each of these guys. So
did this make sense
what we just did over here.
Right? Okay. I got a few yeses. So I'll
say and of course the derivative of the
divergence with respect to any one of
these guys is computed using backb. So
the story so far position invariant
pattern classification can be performed
by scanning 1D scanning for sound 2D
scanning for images but you can have
work in higher dimensions uh 3D and
higher dimensions for high dimensional
data. Scanning is equivalent to
composing one large network with
repeating subnets. So the large network
has shared subnets and learning in the
scan network is performed using back
back propagation but backdrop rules must
be modified to combine gradients from
parameters that share the same value.
Now this applies for the model which I
just saw but it applies in general for
networks with shared parameters.
So any questions so far? Any questions?
Any questions?
If not, I'll go up. I'll wait for 5
seconds for questions.
Okay. If not, let me continue. Okay.
What is 1D scanning in 2D scan? So, I'm
scanning here in 1D.
I'm just going along time, Jandya.
And here I'm scanning in two dimensions,
right?
So
why is W's have to equal to each weight?
I'm not sure what that question means.
So Fernas, how did you construct
when I'm scanning here? I'm just
scanning in one dimension. Right,
Fernas?
Right.
Yeah. So whereas here I'm scanning in
two dimensions. Right. And I'm not sure
who WCJ is but then if you want to train
one large network you need to the
network would be why do we what is
scanning Oman when I'm scanning I'm
using one network here I'm using the
same network out here right
so if I'm using the same network that's
they have it's like having two subnets
with identical parameters is it
We want to
that's what it is. Okay, I'll go on. If
you have any other questions, just hold
the thought till after class because we
need to move on. Okay,
we have a lot to cover.
So here is what we were doing. Now I'm
using this network in my example. I have
four neurons in the first layer, two in
the second, one in the third. And then
we were so if I were if I were to use my
vertical representation
here is what the picture would look
like. And then we were scanning the
input using this network. So at the
first position what happens is that
first the four neurons in the first
layer would compute their outputs.
Then the two neurons in the second layer
would use the outputs of the four four
neurons in the first layer and then
compute their outputs. And then the one
neuron in the third layer is going to
look at the two neurons outputs of the
two neurons in the second layer and then
compute this its output. So is this
computation making sense to you guys?
Yes or no? Is this illustration making
sense?
Okay. So assuming it's making sense then
what happens? These values are computed
at the first position. Then the entire
network moves one step and those values
are computed at the second position.
Then it moves one step. It reads a
different section of the input and these
values are computed at the third
position and so on until you get you
compute these values at every position
in the input and then of course all of
these final outputs are combined into a
softmax. This is the overall computation
performed. These are all the values
computed.
Is this making sense? This picture
everybody.
Okay. Now here's my question. Let's say
I place the network in the first
position and the first layer computes
its outputs. But the first layer is in a
hurry. It's not doesn't wait for the
subsequent layers to compute their
values. It just runs off and computes
all of its values before the second
layer even jumps into action.
And then the second layer and the rest
of the network read the values that this
first layer computed in the first
position and process them. Would this
value be any different than if the
entire network had been computed over
here before it moved on? Would this
value be any different?
It should not right makes no it makes
because the values are going to be
identical. So the output here does not
change due to the reordered computation.
But then now the second layer gets
inspired by layer 1 and says you know
what I don't need to wait for layer two
layer three and it goes off and does its
computations from the outputs of the
first layer and then the third layer
operates on the outputs of the second
layer at this position. Is this guy
going to be any different than if I had
computed the entire network here before
moving on?
No. Right? And so now the third layer
could go off the output here doesn't
change due to the reordered computation
and then the third layer can go off and
do its thing and you can get put the
whole thing have the through the softmax
right so we just change the order of the
computation
how does that look like in terms of code
and and you agree that changing the
order of the computation is not going to
change the output of the softmax here do
you agree with that
yes or no.
Okay. So what really happened? It may
make more sense if you look at it
through code.
In code, we've scanned the input at each
if you were just looking through at this
example, you scanned the input at each
as you scanned at each position, you
pulled out a segment and then you put it
through the MLP and computed an output
at this position. Right? If I expand
this out, it's going to look like this.
You're scanning the input
at each position. You're taking this
input and for the first layer of the
network, you're looking at this entire
section. And from this entire section,
you compute a Z. From the Z, you compute
a Y. Right? Then this then you go
through the next layer. The next layer
uses this Y to compute its Z. And then
it comput its Y. Then the next layer
uses this Y to compute its Z and its Y
and so on. So what has happened is that
at each position you're going through
all the layers of the network. Right?
Is this code making sense?
Okay. Now but all the action is
happening inside the innermost loop. Is
it not?
All the actions happening inside is
happening inside the innermost loop. Yes
or no? Right. So if I change the So the
first loop is over time. The second loop
is over layers actions here. If I change
the order of the two outermost loops. If
I put L first and T T T T T T T T T T T
T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T
T T T T T T T T T T next would it change
the overall computation of this
algorithm?
Keeping in mind that all the action is
really inside the innermost loop.
>> It would not. Right. So
that's basically what we did. We scan
the input. We we we
scan the input with each layer before
moving on to the next layer when we did
this computation.
That's what happened over here. That
make sense to everybody,
right? Yes. Okay.
So same thing in 2D. I'd be scanning the
input for the desired object using a
using an MLP. This is my input. There I
have some hidden layers and then there's
a final output layer. So at each
position, the network computes an
output. This is the set of outputs
computed from each position. These guys
are put through a softmax or a or or
something more complex maybe for the
final decision. But then what's
happening at each neuron? At each
position, the neuron is the first layer
neurons are looking at all of these
values and computing an aine value and
putting it through an activation. Right?
So let's look at this first guy. Like in
the 1D case, this guy, he's in a hurry.
He doesn't wait for the rest of the
network. He goes off and computes his
entire input, right? In fact, it's not
just him, but all of his siblings, they
do the same. So these four neurons go
off and compute their compute their
output values without waiting for the
rest of the network. So now if I want to
find out if there's a flower in this
position, what would I do? If I want to
position, what would I do? Anyone?
What would I do?
Somebody
I verified all the results. I need to
look at the value that each of these
neurons computed when they were scanning
this location. Those would be these four
guys, right?
And so these four can now be put through
the rest of the network.
And that would tell me if there was a
flower over here.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
That make sense to you?
Right. Okay. I'm assuming it did.
So
uh
each
at each position each of them is this
guy is computed for instance on this
position. So also this guy is computed
from this position. This guy is also
computed from this position. This one
these four are computed from this
position and so on.
Okay.
And so to classify a specific window, I
just pick up the first level activations
from those positions corresponding to
that from the uh outputs corresponding
to that position and pass them on to the
next layer.
But then I can recurse the logic. The
second layer neurons don't need to wait
for the output, right? The second layer
neurons can now scan the outputs of the
first layer neurons. But then keep this
in mind. The first layer neurons, they
were just looking at the entire input.
Each neuron was looking at all of these
guys in the input, right? The second
layer neurons are simultaneously looking
at the outputs of all the first layer
neurons
in that position. That make sense
that the second layer what these second
layer neurons are doing, this guy has to
look at the outputs of all four neurons.
So it has to look at all four of these
guys.
Make sense?
Yes or no? Okay. So, Christian, how do
you know the number of you're scanning?
So, it's going to depend on the size of
the input, right?
And so, now the second layer neurons can
go off and scan the first layer, first
layer neuron outputs. And then if I want
to find out if there was a a flower over
here, I just read the outputs of the
second layer neurons when they were
looking at these positions in the
outputs of the first layer neurons. And
these are the outputs that the first
layer neurons produced when they were
looking over here. And so now the output
of this neuron is going to tell me there
was a flower over here or not. Did this
make sense? This did this illustration
make sense?
Okay, so it's what we will do
and so we can recurse it and we can make
a map for the third layer neurons itself
also. The map is a flower. This neuron
which scans these two outputs
simultaneously
is going to creating a map for the each
location of the original image. Right?
Yes. Say yes. So each of these neurons
is scanning the input. Okay. How do you
find the corresponding position? If I
look at any if I look at this guy, this
one came from here and here, right? And
these came from here and here and here
and here. And each of those four came
from here. So you can just work your way
back and find out where they came from
if you're interested. Right?
And so to detect a picture at any
location, you only need to look at the
corresponding location in the output
map. And of course, you can put the
whole thing from max or soft max to
decide if the picture has a flower.
Right? And very often instead of drawing
this as a map, we'll just draw this
final layer output as a flat uh you know
as as a flat uh layer of outputs, flat
arrangement of outputs. It's called
flattering. And these are put through
max of max.
So what happened over here again
when you were scanning you were going
over X you were going over Y at each
position you were pulling out an a you
know this was your image you going over
X you were going over Y at each position
you pulled out a segment you passed it
through an MLP and you got a Y value
over here and the collection of Y's was
put through a softmax. Right?
But then if you look closely at what at
what's going on
within each position, you're going
through the layers at each layer. For
the first layer alone, you're looking at
a region of the input.
But then from this region, you're
computing a Z at each position. Each
layer is computing a Z and then a Y.
Then the next layer is looking at the Y
to compute its own Z and then it's
computing its own Y. And then the next
layer is computing the aine term and its
own y and so on till you get to the end
of the network. All of this is
happening. You go through the layers at
each position. So once again and then
the collection of the final layer
outputs is put through a softmax. So is
this code making sense to you guys? Yes
sir.
Okay. Once again all the action is in
the middle right is is in the innermost
loop. Right? all the actions in the NMO
slope
which means if I change the order
the output should not change correct
yes or no
so the L can go out the X and Y can come
in and the network's output doesn't
change so that's what happened over here
each layer is scanning the outputs of
the previous layer without waiting for
subsequent layers all we did was change
the order of the computation and you
should still get the same output. So the
story so far position and variant
pattern classification can be performed
by scanning the input for a target
pattern. Scanning is equivalent to
composing a large network with shared
subnets. The operations in scanning the
input with a full network can be
reordered as scanning the input with
individual neurons in the first layer to
produce scan maps of the input and then
jointly scanning the map of outputs by
all the neurons in the previous layers
by neurons and subsequent layers. So
here is our second poll.
These are true false questions. I'm
going to give you only 35 seconds.
10 seconds, guys.
Five.
All right, let me stop the post.
What's the answer to the first question?
True or false? Second one,
true or false? Also true, right? Both
are true. Beautiful.
So what's happening
in the basic network? In the original
framework, the entire NLP was looking
for a flower-like pattern at each
location.
So what happened? The first layer
neurons look at this entire window to
extract a window level features because
these these neurons are looking at this
entire window. Right? So these each of
these neurons is going to detect a
flower, a feature that's typical of a
flower that the rest of the neural
network can operate on to determine if
there's a there's a flower there or not.
Which means the neuron is responsible
for extracting flowersized features.
Each of these neurons bears a tremendous
responsibility. It must detect flower-
sized features and then subsequent with
all the arrangements and then the
subsequent layers are just looking at
single pixels in the outputs of the
previous layers.
Does that make sense?
The first layer neurons are looking for
this entire window. But the second layer
neurons are only looking for a single
pixel from the positions of these guys.
The third layer neurons are looking just
for single pixels over here. That's what
was happening. Yes or no?
This may okay. So
uh and
but then I can why is that? Because this
guy is only looking at these the these
these neurons outputs, right? These two
neurons are only looking at the outputs
of these two neurons at any given
position. Right?
I have this window. If I'm trying to
perform detect if there's a flower,
these neurons will each produce one
output. And then the second layer,
neurons are going to look at these four
outputs. Yes,
right. You could scan a pixel at a time
or you could jump. Okay, we'll get to
that. But then I can distribute the
pattern matching over two layers and
still achieve the same same block
analysis at the second layer. How the
first layer neurons can look at a
smaller section of the wind of the image
say this size and then scan the input
with this smaller window. Then the
second layer neurons can actually and it
ar this first layer neurons will arrange
their outputs in the same shape as the
input itself. Then the second layer
neurons will actually look at a window
of outputs
from the out first layer neurons. So
what happens when this neuron looks at
this window of outputs? It's effectively
looking at all regions of the input that
were invoked when any of these outputs
were produced by the first layer
neurons. So now although the first layer
neurons individually only looked at this
much the second layer neuron is now
going to look at a flower sized pattern.
Did this make sense?
Right. And so
uh this guy is looking at these inputs
and so it's looking at every portion of
the input that was invoked in computing
any of these highlighted dots which
would be the entire flower sized window.
So the first layer layer neuron
evaluates smaller blocks of pixels. The
second one evaluates windows of outputs
from the first layer. This effectively
evaluates a larger window of the
original image. And what has happened
over here? This window has now been
distributed over two layers. Now the
first layer neurons are no longer
looking for flower- sized patterns.
They're looking for smaller patterns
like say the size of a sele or a petal
or a steamman. And then the second layer
neuron is looking at all of these
outputs and saying so let's say this guy
detects flowers angles this way and or
upwards right and this guy is detecting
flowers angle this way and this guy is
detecting something like stammans right
and this guy is looking at petals angle
this way so sorry petals. So then this
this neuron is saying that when this guy
has fired at these two positions and
when this guy has fired at this position
and when this guy has fired in the
center and when this guy has fired over
here I get this kind of a pattern which
kind of looks like a portion of a
flower.
Does that make sense?
Yes. No,
>> right. Okay. And so what we did was we
let the lower first layer neurons look
for smaller patterns and the second
layer neurons comp combine them in
position to make decisions about the
larger image. And then the second layer
neurons can scan the maps produced by
the first layer neurons with windows to
produce their outputs at every position.
And now if the next layer neurons must
detect if there's a flower out here, it
just needs to look at these outputs from
the second layer neurons. This make
sense to everybody?
Yes. Now
okay. So
and now
to compute that the third layer neurons
can scan the maps by the the second
layer neurons and their outputs can be
combined using a softmax to detect if
there's a flower over here.
You're still scanning but you're
scanning with a shared parameter network
with one minor modification. What is
that? Right. So this is exactly the same
as before but then within the network
itself you have further sharing of
parameters. Why? So look at the first
layer neurons. The first layer neurons
are looking at small windows this size.
So the same so if I have this as my
network
this black neuron is looking at each of
these nine outputs
to produce these nine outputs. This is
the this is like having nine copies of
this black neuron. one looking at each
position. Do you agree? When this black
neuron scans this portion of the input,
it's like having nine copies of the
neuron looking static copies looking at
each of these positions. Right? So
similarly, these when the second neuron
scans the input, it's like having nine
copies of the second neuron. When the
third neuron scans this input, it's like
having nine copies of the third neuron.
And then subsequently when the next
level neurons
uh look at the outputs of at windows
from the first level neurons they're
actually looking at all 27 of these
values
that make sense.
Yes. No. Yeah. So this is the network
but then within the network these three
nine neurons have the same parameters.
These three nine neurons have the same
parameters and these three nine neurons
have the same parameters. So the network
that is scanning the input has shared
parameters within itself also. So this
is actually means that the network that
analyzes individual blocks it is itself
a shared parameter network.
That making sense?
Yes. No. Okay.
And now I can do the same thing over
three layers. The first layer neurons
can be looking at even smaller windows
regions of the input and scanning it.
The next layer neurons can be looking at
windows of these guys. When it's looking
at windows of these guys, it's basically
looking at the entire region of the
input that's invoked in computing any of
these highlighted dots. And so then the
third layer, neurons could be looking at
windows of these guys. When they're
doing that, they're looking at all
portions of the input that are invoked
in computing or any of these dots. Which
is to say, it's looking at any region of
these maps which were invoked in
computing any of these highlighted dots
and which in turn is looking at any
region of the input which was invoked in
the computation of any of these uh of
these highlighted dots. Right? So
your this neuron is now looking at the
full flower sized image, but it's
distributed the patterns in the flower
over three layers. This make sense
what we just did,
right? So
now we're not compressing anything.
We're just distributing the patterns.
Right? The final classification for the
entire image use the outputs from all
locations as seen in the final map.
Right? How does the recombination happen
since the neuron layers scan the entire
input? No, they don't. Right? So this
guy it's it's
and John the dude let's wait for after
class. Okay.
So what happened is that we are still
scanning the input
for a flower but the network that's
scanning the input is itself a shared
parameter network. And so once again
this entire network can be thought of as
one giant network where the subnets
themselves have shared parameters within
themselves.
This make sense to everybody?
Yes or no? Okay. So
codewise what was happening earlier you
were scanning left to right within each
section you were pulling out an image
within each position you're pulling out
a section of the image and passing it
through an NLP and then passing the
collection of outputs through the
softmax. So when we changed it, changed
the ordering, we were going through the
layers at each layer. Each layer was
scanning the input. The f the first
layer alone was looking at an entire
section of the input. Subsequent layers
were just looking at one position,
right? From the outputs of the previous
layer. And so this was what we were
doing when we were not distributing the
patterns across layers. But now the
pseudo code becomes even simpler.
What happened? What happens is that the
first layer neurons are looking at
little sections of the input of this
width. Then the second uh sorry no
then the second layer neurons are going
to be looking at windows
of the outputs of the first layer
neurons. the third layer neurons are
going to be looking at windows of the
outputs of the second layer neurons and
so on. So the so this uh extra clause
that we had earlier which said that only
the first layer was looking at windows
and the rest were looking at individual
pixels even that went away and uh the
overall code became even simpler. Each
layer first pulls out a window of input
of values from the output of the
previous layer and then computes the
aine aine terms and output terms. So is
this modified code making sense? Each
layer scans the input at each position
it pulls out a window from the output of
the previous layer and processes it.
Right?
So the question is this whole operation
of scanning with a window this is what's
called a convolution and so this entire
network is what is called a
convolutional neural network
overall state of code for convolutional
neural network that I showed that for
the 2D case what about the 1D case same
thing right so in the 1D scan the this
it's called a time delay neural network
it's primarily used for speech
recognition
The first layer in your without
distribution the first layer is if you
say if you're looking for the word
welcome right then the first layer would
be looking for a welcome sized region of
the input and the subsequent layers
would be working on the operation
outputs of the first layer.
But then when you begin to distribute it
the first layer is going to look for
smaller uh regions of the input. Maybe
you're looking for uh regions which are
the width of maybe a single phone,
right? And so the first layer neurons
are going to be scanning the input over
smaller regions of the input. And then
the second layer neurons are going to be
looking at regions of the input, right?
They want to look at a larger region of
the input. So if they want to look at a
larger region of the input, they must
now look at multiple
columns from the output of the first
layer. And then they may learn that you
know that if the first neuron fires over
here and the sec and the sec and the and
the second neuron fires over here and
the third neuron fires over here,
there's probably a hello, right? So uh
they can actually detect that. That
makes sense.
Sorry guys.
Did this make sense to all of you guys?
Okay. And so the second layer neurons
will be looking at a region of the first
layer outputs. They're going to be
looking at a bigger region. And what is
the benefit over here? Instead of having
the first layer neurons look for hello
sized patterns, the first layer neurons
could now be looking at individual phone
names and the second layer neurons can
now combine these to make global
decisions about whether the word has
occurred or not. Right? And you can and
so the second layer neurons are going to
be looking over this sized windows. You
can distribute this further. The third
layer neurons could be looking at
regions of the second layer outputs
where each of these is looking at a
region of the first layer output. So the
overall uh region of the input that the
third layer neuron is looking at is much
wider. And so now you can instead of
burdening just the first layer neurons
with looking trying to detect welcomes
sized patterns. You can distribute the
patterns and look for smaller units like
phone names or things smaller than
phonms and compose them into the overall
pattern that looks like the word
welcome. That make sense
to everybody?
And so
uh that's what we do. This is the 1D
scan version. And of course the final
aggregator which could be a perceptron
aggregates the output to say does this
recording have the target word which
could be welcome. Right? This is what's
called a time delay neural network. A 1D
scan network is called a time delay
neural network or a 1D CNN. So that
leads us to the third pole.
45 seconds, guys.
So, Jina, we I'm not sure how we learn
as children, right? There are all kinds
of hypotheses about it, but I don't
think there's anything that's been
substantiated, but this is how neural
networks do it. convolutional approach
to it.
10 seconds, guys.
All right, let me end this forward.
And can we tell can anybody tell me
which of these statements are true?
Nondistributed scanning requires the
output maps of the neurons to be
arranged in the same shape as the input
chest two and three right because if
you're not looking at windows
then you can arrange them any hard how
the distributed scan is looking at
windows which means the arrangement is
important the non-distributed scan is
not looking at arrangements so only two
and three are true right fantastic you
guys are
So why bother with all of this
distribution?
Three reasons. Distribution forces
hierarchical representations with
localized patterns in local layers. So
they're more generalizable. They result
in fewer computations because you can
reuse computations and far fewer number
of parameters.
So how is that? Let's look at the first
reason. Remember in the second class or
even the first class how we composed a
double pentagon decision boundary. Did
we did we burden the first layer neurons
with trying to detect both pentagons all
at once or did the first layer neurons
just compose?
What happened? The first layer neurons
found bits of the first pentagon. The
second layer neurons found the
individual pentagons. The third layer
composed them together. Right? By
distributing the pattern across multiple
layers, we made the problem very simple,
right?
And we saw that when we try to make it
differently, when we put the entire
burden on the first layer, the network
can become impossibly large. Do you
remember that?
Yes or no? Right? And this is true,
right? If you are trying to detect
digits in these LED patterns, you'd want
the first layer neurons to find indiv
individual bars. The second layer,
second layer to compose them into
patterns, the final layer to take
decision. So when you distribute the
pattern hierarchically over many layers,
your model can become much simpler and
much more generalizable. So you want to
encourage such hierarchical learning.
It's more data and parameter efficient.
Which leads us to reasons two and three,
right? fewer computations and far fewer
parameters. Let's look at the fewer
computations. First, let's look at a
case where I have a nondistributed
network. So the first layer I'm trying
to find patterns which are eight inputs
wide. So the first layer is looking at
eight inputs. The second layer is
looking at just the outputs of the first
layer. The third layer is looking as
just the outputs of the second layer. So
then this entire network performs this
computation here. And then when I'm
scanning this entire network performs
all of its computations at each position
here I've have uh uh stepped forward by
two time steps at a time. Is this
illustration making sense that the these
are the computations you'd be performing
right? So now
that's just one. Yes. Is this picture
making sense to you guys? The rest of
you.
Okay,
I'm just using a simpler picture. Okay,
so if I had N1 neurons in the first
layer, N2 in the second layer, and N3 in
the third layer, and N1 neurons were
looking at eight inputs each of
dimension D, how many parameters would I
have? How many weights would I have in
this setup, guys? The first layer has N1
neurons. It's looking at eight vectors
each of dimension D. So, how many
parameters does the first layer have?
Anybody?
How many will it have? The inputs are
8D, correct? There are N1 neurons. So,
the first layer has 8D N1 neurons. That
make sense?
Yes. No.
Now, the second layer has N2 neurons and
they're all looking at N1 neurons. How
many neuron parameters does the second
layer have?
How many neurons is N2 N1, right? And
how many neurons parameters does the
third layer have
this guy?
N3 and two, right? Fantastic. So you get
the idea. That's how many parameters we
need. Okay.
Now
let's assume
a distributed network. So the first
layer neurons are only looking at two
time steps. But the second layer neurons
are looking at four of these guys,
right? So what happens? These guys are
all identical. Meaning these weights are
the same as these weights are the same
as these weights are the same as these
weights, right? But this guy is looking
at each of these outputs with a
different set of weights. So if I want
to see the to if I if if I want to
compute the total number of parameters
over here, what I would have is if I had
n1 neurons over here and this is two two
time steps. How many parameters would
this would the would the first layer
neurons have? How many parameters would
the first layer neurons have?
Yeah, anybody?
It's going to be 2 B and one, right?
Correct. How many parameters with the
second layer neurons have?
It's going to be four N1 N2 and the
third layer of neurons is just N2 N3.
Right? So you get it. Beautiful. Now
let's compare this. So these are all the
parameters you have. That's going to be
2D n1 + 4 n1 n2 plus n2 n3. Yes, the
first layer has shared parameters
because the first layer is scanning,
right? It's looking at inputs two
inputs at a time and the second layer is
looking at four of the first layer
inputs outputs. So the second layer is
effectively looking at a width of eight.
That answer your question.
Yes.
Okay guys, I'm now
if I want a standard network with the
same number of parameters,
here's what you're going to have. There
are four N four same number of neurons.
There are four N1 neurons in the first
layer. The second layer is N2, the third
layer is N3. These two networks have the
same number of neurons. This one is
distributed. This one is not. Right? So
this guy is going to have 4 N1 * 8 which
is 32 N1 parameters in the first layer.
This one has 2 N1
neurons in the first layer. So do you
see the difference over here? This is
just 2 N1. This is 32 N1.
The rest of them are the same. Right?
Yes or no?
Guys, please respond quickly because I'm
running out of time. Right. And so you
can see how this can result in a massive
reduction in parameters.
So
now let's look at how you can save
computation. Right? If I'm distributed
computing networks and I'm looking at
inputs 8 wide, then this network is
scanning the input here, then it's
striding by two and then it's scanning
the input starting from here. Is there
any computation that I performed when
looking at this region of the input that
I could reuse when I'm looking at this
region of the input? Can you find any
reused computation?
irreusable computation
guys.
Yes or no?
Which ones?
These three outputs can be reused,
right? Because they have already been
computed. And so when you actually have
this distributed parameter computation
network, you can see that you can also
reuse the computation. And so
not only do you get far fewer
parameters, you're going to be able to
reuse the outputs from diff previous
positions, which means you're going to
get large additional benefits in compute
as well. That make sense to all of you?
Yes. No. All right. And so, and if I do
this over three layers, I have more
examples. I'm running out of time, so I
won't uh spend time on these examples,
but it's basically the same thing. The
more you distribute the network over,
the more layers you distribute the
network over, the greater the comput the
uh uh benefit you get in terms of the
number of parameters and the greater the
benefit you get in terms of reused
computation. So uh that's for 1D scans.
Same thing over here, right? If I'm
scanning
then you can see that how if these guys
are scanning something this sized when I
go from one position to the other all of
these
can be reused right same as before the
illustrations in 2D are not as clear as
in the 1D case but it's the same thing
all over again and so in fact we have
some arithmetic I won't go through the
math right now because we're out of time
but basically what we find that in a
very trivial example if I do not have uh
a distributed scan
I might need 1,034
parameters weights whereas a distributed
network which is looking at analyzing
windows of the same size is going to
need only
194 parameters.
So the benefits can be very large.
Uh so
in fact as the networks get larger and
larger the gains in compute and
parameters can be many orders of
magnitude. So distribution forces
localized patterns in lower layers which
is more generalizable. You can have
large sometimes orders of magnitude
reduction in the number of parameters
and significant gains from shared
computation. The key intuition is that
regardless of the distribution, we can
view the network still as scanning the
picture with an MLP. The only difference
is the manner in which the parameters
are shared in the MLP. So the story so
far position and variant pattern
classification can be performed by
scanning the input for a target pattern.
The operations in scanning the input
with a full network can be reordered as
scanning the input with individual
neurons in the first layer to produce
scan maps of the input and then jointly
scanning the maps of outputs by all the
neurons in previous layers by subsequent
layers. The scanning block can be
distributed over multiple layers of the
network resulting in significant
reduction in the total number of
parameters and compute. So here is the
final hole.
30 seconds, guys.
Okay, 5 seconds.
Let me end this right here. Which are
the statements that are true?
All of them.
All. No, the last one. It doesn't reduce
the memory requirement because you still
have to compute all the intermediate
values. It just reduces the compute and
the number of parameters. Right? The
intermediate variables are going to be
the same. It's just that you have shared
parameters. So some final touches, some
terminology, filters and receptive
fields, shrinking the maps. So you can
think of the entire operation as maps of
the entire image. The first layer
neurons look for patterns of a small
size and they scan the input and produce
maps. So you can think of these first
layer neurons as repainting the input
with certain features highlighted. So
for example, if this guy is looking for
petals, then anytime it finds a petal,
it's going to highlight it and make that
brighter. So each of these first layer
neurons are basically repainting
uh the redrawing the input with some
features highlighted.
uh then so
the second layer neurons are going to be
looking at regions of the first layer
neurons and if they detect certain
patterns that they're looking for
they're going to highlight those. So the
second layer neurons are also repainting
the input with some kinds of patterns
highlighted and then the third layer
neurons which scan the outputs of the
second layer neurons are also doing the
same.
So the set of weights for each of the
scanning neurons is generally called a
filter. Each filter scans for a pattern
in the map that it operates on.
And the region of the input that each of
these neurons looks at is also called a
receptive field. Sometimes even the
pattern that it's trying to detect is
also called a receptive field. But the
receptive field is the region of the
input that the neuron is looking at. And
if you're trying to find out what
pattern each neuron is detecting, it's
easy for the first layer neurons. The
weights of the filters will tell you
what patterns it's looking for. For
later neurons, later higher layer
neurons, you're going to have to do some
additional computation. Uh, and depends
on the receptive field and stride of the
lower layer neurons. Then the final
layer neurons are generally outputs are
not kept as an map but they're kind of
straightened into a vector to for for
further processing. So this is just
terminology. This restructuring is
called flattening.
The other thing that many of you mention
is as you scan how freak how big is the
step size you take. The default step
size is one. Which is why if you have a
step size of one, then this map produced
by the first layer neurons is going to
be approximately the same size as the
input except for some edge effects.
Which is why it can highlight certain
patterns. But then the neurons map may
also be allowed to step by more than one
pixel at a time in which case the maps
that these neurons produce are going to
shrink.
And the shrink factor by which they
shrink depends on the stride by which
the scan is performed.
So
CNN's with strides when you're scanning
instead of taking moving forward by one
step at a time, one pixel at a time,
you'll be moving forward by by a stride
length. And the output map is going to
be shrunk by a factor that's equal to
the stride length. These are all just
final touches.
Then there's one final operation where
we account for jitter where we just say
that you know if the second layer neuron
is saying this neuron must which looks
for petals must find a petal here and
this neuron which looks for seles must
find a sele here and so on. If this
guy's output if the petal position moves
by one pixel does it stop being a
flower?
If the pedal position jiggle jiggles by
just once no right so you want to
account for some jitter and variance and
the jitter and variance is performed
using an operation called pulling that
we will see in the next class. So what
exactly is pulling
in pulling it's uh you'll be looking at
windows of the outputs and just picking
the largest value. So you would say that
if I find a petal in any one of these
four regions, I found a petal in
approximately the right area. So and I
can use that to compose a flower. So
pulling it sort of
introduces variation to minor shifts in
subpattern positions and allows for and
makes the pattern detection more robust
to such variations.
So here's the overall structure of the
network.
It has this entire thing is called a
convolutional neural network. You have
neurons which scan the input windows of
the with small windows and subsequent
layer neurons which scan the maps
produced by the previous layers in small
windows all the way through the network.
You may have some additional components
for pooling components in the middle and
then the outputs of the final layer and
you know they're passed through some
decision mechanism. This is a
convolutional neural network. This was
the first convolutional neural network
created for analyzing images by Yan
Leon. This is what he won his touring
award for. So he did this for emnest
images.
The first layer consisted of uh five
convolutional neurons because this first
layer had five neurons which we're
looking at I think five + 5 windows.
Then there was some cooling which
reduced the size of the map. Then the
next layer had I think 10 neurons. So
there were 10 neurons in the second
layer which scanned these guys to create
their maps. Then there was one more
polling layer and the outputs of these
guys were put through an MLP for
decisions and it was the first time that
it showed neural networks could actually
work for position and variant uh digit
recognition. So to finish our story
just ending
uh the scan block can be distributed
over multiple layers for efficiency. At
each layer a scan by a neuron may be
optionally followed by a max or pooling
operation to account for deformation.
For 2D or higher dimensional scans the
structure is called a convolutional
neural network. For 1D scans along the
time axis it's called a time delay
neural network or a 1D CNN. I'll stop
here first.